Finding Aid for the Albert H. and Emma M. Wheeler papers 1938-1994 (bulk 1960-1977)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Albert H. and Emma M. Wheeler papers 1938-1994, 1960-1977
Wheeler, Albert Harold, 1915-1994.
6 linear feet
Albert and Emma Wheeler were community and civil rights leaders from Ann Arbor, Michigan. Albert Wheeler was also professor of microbiology and dermatology at the University of Michigan. In addition, he and his wife helped to establish the local chapter of the NAACP. Albert Wheeler served as mayor of Ann Arbor, 1975 to 1978. The series in the collection are Personal/Biographical; NAACP/Civil Rights Activities; Mayoralty Files; University of Michigan; and Photographs. The collection documents the Wheelers' devotion to the cause of civil rights and their involvement with numerous civil rights and community organizations. The collection also includes Albert Wheeler's mayoralty files.
9428 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Albert H. and Emma M. Wheeler (Donor no. 8176 ) in 1993. Additional material was added in 1995 by Emma M. Wheeler.
The collection is open for research.
Albert Harold Wheeler was born in St. Louis, Missouri on December 11, 1915 and it was here that he spent his childhood. In 1936 he received a Bachelor of Arts degree from Lincoln University in Pennsylvania and in 1938 a Master of Science degree in microbiology from Iowa State College.
Emma Monteith Wheeler grew up in Columbia, South Carolina where, at the age of seven, she and her sister were witnesses to the lynching of a black man and the slashing of a pregnant black woman by a mob of whites. These events helped to define her resolve to fight for racial justice and equality.
It was at the University of Michigan in the late 1930s that the Wheelers met. They were both students in the School of Public Health, were awarded Master of Science in Public Health degrees in 1938 and married on April 15, 1938. In spite of the racial biases prevalent in Ann Arbor at the time, they chose to settle here and buy a home. Emma Wheeler chose to stay at home and raise their three daughters rather than pursue a professional career.
Albert Wheeler completed his Ph.D. in public health at the University of Michigan in 1944 and was hired by Dr. Reuben L. Kahn as a research associate in the Serology Laboratory. In 1952, Dr. Arthur Curtis appointed Wheeler to a newly created position in microbiology and he thus became the first African-American ever named to a tenure track position at the University of Michigan. He held joint appointments as assistant professor - with subsequent promotions to associate and full professor - in the departments of microbiology and dermatology. His specialty within his department was venereal disease, more exactly, syphilis. When Wheeler retired in 1981 he was named Professor Emeritus of Microbiology and Immunology.
As one of a handful of African-American professionals in Ann Arbor in the 1940s, Albert Wheeler was among the founding members of the Civic Forum, a forerunner to the NAACP and Congress for Racial Equality (CORE). The Civic Forum focused on issues relevant to the improvement of the lives of African-Americans in Ann Arbor, notably in the areas of housing, education and jobs. In the early 1950s members of the Forum approached the Ann Arbor Democratic Party which had been largely shut out of local politics with the idea of joining forces. These two groups formed an important coalition that became known as the "civil rights" party. Because of their urging, the city of Ann Arbor established the Human Relations Commission. The commission's purpose was to investigate discrimination in the city of Ann Arbor. Albert Wheeler served on the first Human Relations Commission. The Wheelers were also instrumental in founding a new Ann Arbor chapter of the NAACP in 1957, prior attempts at forming an active chapter having failed. This organization grew in strength as Emma Wheeler served as its president through 1971. Although the Civic Forum functioned for several years beyond 1957, the rebirth of the NAACP took on many of the Forum's issues, and the organization was eventually absorbed by the NAACP.
Housing, education, employment, legal justice, and community education were among the issues addressed by the NAACP. Emma Wheeler led the NAACP in fights leading to the passage of Ann Arbor's Fair Housing Ordinance, the first of its kind in the state of Michigan. It took several years of debate for passage to occur, including nightly picketing in front of City Hall for two years by members of the NAACP and the Congress for Racial Equality (CORE). Two fair housing laws were passed in 1965 and 1966. Prior to this, blacks were essentially told where they could live in the city of Ann Arbor, as specified in housing ads. Emma Wheeler was also concerned about matters of race as they affected the public school system. She worked to establish recognition of the needs of black high school students, to redefine school discipline policies that tended to be racially discriminatory, and to design the first racial integration plan for Ann Arbor public schools. Under the urging of the Wheelers and the NAACP, the city of Ann Arbor passed the Human Rights Ordinance in 1970. This anti-discrimination legislation included prohibitions on housing and other forms of discrimination.
Albert Wheeler was active on the state level as well. In 1961 he conceived and submitted a proposal to the Michigan Constitutional Convention that resulted in the establishment of the Michigan Civil Rights Commission. This commission was the first and only such commission of its kind in the United States. Dr. Wheeler was instrumental in convincing Governor John Swainson to obtain the required number of delegate signatures to place the proposal for consideration. He also played key roles in the Statewide Housing Conference and the Michigan Welfare League. From 1966 to 1969 Albert Wheeler served as president of the Michigan Conference of NAACP Branches. It was during these years that a great deal of racial confrontation took place in the state of Michigan, including the Detroit riots and the march from St. Joseph to Benton Harbor for housing integration.
Dr. Wheeler also served as the first chairman of the Washtenaw County Citizens for Economic Opportunity Committee and chaired the Planning Committee that developed the local Model Cities program. The program provided health care, dental care, legal assistance, and child care at low cost to clients who could not otherwise afford such services. Emma Wheeler served as chairwoman of the Model Cities Health Center from 1971 until it was shut down in 1981 amidst controversy over its finances.
In 1975 Albert Wheeler was elected the first black mayor of the city of Ann Arbor. This election was decided under a preferential voting system. When neither Wheeler nor his opponent, incumbent mayor James Stephenson, garnered a majority of the votes, the second choice of those voting for the third party candidate was counted. The result was a Wheeler victory. In 1977, he was reelected by one vote over his opponent Republican candidate Louis Belcher. This election was disputed by Belcher when it was discovered that several voters, who did not actually live in the city of Ann Arbor, had been registered by the city clerk. Wheeler subsequently lost a court ordered election to Belcher in 1978. While in office, Mayor Wheeler established both a city Human Services Department and a Fair Rental Practices Commission.
In addition to his civil rights and political interests Albert Wheeler was actively involved in the Catholic Archdiocese of Detroit. From 1970 to 1974 he was on leave from his University of Michigan appointment to serve as Director of the Department of Christian Service. In 1971 he was appointed by Cardinal Dearden as the first chairman of the National Campaign for Human Development Committee. This program collects monies from Catholic parishes and distributes them to local communities for self-help and self-empowerment projects.
Albert Wheeler received various gubernatorial appointments during the course of his public life. He was a member of the Commission to Study Problems of the Aging, the Michigan Advisory Committee to Study the Financing of Public Schools, and the Commission to Study Problems of Youth. From 1967 to 1976 he also served on the Michigan Advisory Committee to the U.S. Civil Rights Commission.
The Wheelers continued their active role in the political life of Ann Arbor as members of the Ann Arbor Democratic Party following retirement. They have long been recognized for their willingness to assist those in need through their assistance with housing, employment, and moral support. Albert Wheeler died on April 4, 1994.
The Albert H. and Emma M. Wheeler collection documents the involvement of this couple in the growth and development of the civil rights movement in Ann Arbor. The collection includes in part the mayoralty files of Albert Wheeler, mayor of Ann Arbor from 1975 to 1978. The collection is divided into six series: Personal/Biographical, NAACP/Civil Rights Issues, Mayoral Files, University of Michigan, Photographs and Medical.
Subjects:
Afro-Americans--Michigan.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Mayors--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Politics and government.; Civil rights--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Democratic Party (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Discrimination in housing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan. Civil Rights Commission.; Municipal government--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Michigan Branch.; Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Washtenaw County Citizen's Committee for Economic Opportunity.; Wheeler, Albert Harold, 1915-1994.; Wheeler, Emma M.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal 1958-1993
  The Personal/Biographical series (1958-1993; 4 inches) contains several vita of Albert Wheeler, biographical commentaries written by him, editorial articles he wrote for the Ann Arbor News, as well as a folder of newspaper clippings written in the late 1980s and early 1990s, often as tributes to the Wheelers and their work. A folder of Ann Arbor Democratic Party materials dating from 1958 to 1990 documents the Wheelers' activity in this organization. Of interest are three folders of speeches given by Albert Wheeler, which provide insight into his convictions and beliefs. Many of the speeches complement materials in other parts of the collection. The researcher will also find Wheeler speeches under various topical headings throughout the collection. This series is organized alphabetically.
  - Ann Arbor News Articles 1960-1990 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Democratic Party 1958-1990 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Information (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1980-1993 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1989 (Box 1)
  - Honors and Awards undated (Box 1)
  - Obituaries, Albert H. Wheeler 1994 (Box 1)
  - Speeches
    - 1963-1967 (Box 1)
    - Undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
- NAACP/Civil Rights Issues 1947-1989
  The NAACP/Civil Rights Issues series (1947-1989; 3 linear feet) is the largest in the collection, and consists of materials relating to civil rights and to the Wheelers' involvement in civil rights organizations, especially the NAACP, the Ann Arbor Human Relations Commission, and the Washtenaw County Citizens for Economic Opportunity. This series is divided into five subseries: NAACP Files, Ann Arbor Concerns, Washtenaw County Concerns, Topical Files and Presidential Files. The first four of these subseries document the civil rights movement and the NAACP in Ann Arbor and the immediate area. Much of what is contained in these files is supporting material, such as organizational reports used by the NAACP in their decision making processes. The Presidential Files subseries document Wheeler's tenure as president of the Michigan Conference of NAACP Branches. The folder headings are, for the most part, those designated by the Wheelers. The series is arranged alphabetically.
  - NAACP Files
    Within the NAACP Files subseries, the activities of the Ann Arbor branch of the NAACP are documented through a combination of minutes, official statements and reactions, and correspondence with various national NAACP offices, including that of executive director Roy Wilkins. Additional statements and reactions of the NAACP may also be found under topical headings in this series. A small number of early newsletters of African-American organizations in addition to the NAACP are present.
    - Black Forum Organization 1968 (Box 1)
    - Brotherhood Eye Newsletter 1963 (Box 1)
    - Community Information Series, Judge Crockett 1974 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - NAACP National Offices
        - Director of Branches 1960-1968 (Box 1)
        - Executive Secretary (Roy Wilkins) 1960-1971 (Box 1)
        - Field Director 1960-1970 (Box 1)
        - General Counsel 1960 (Box 1)
        - Legal Defense and Education Fund 1960-1967 (Box 1)
        - Membership Office 1960-1970 (Box 1)
        - Treasurer 1966-1967 (Box 1)
        - Washington Bureau 1959-1971 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous 1961-1990, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Education Committee 1958-1969 (Box 1)
    - Hill, Mr. and Mrs. Jesse, Grievances 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Incoming Democratic Party 1969 (Box 1)
    - Minutes and Agendas 1963-1973 (Box 1)
    - Mississippi Emergency Relief Fund 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - NAACP Newsletter 1958, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Organizational Information, Statements, Policies 1962-1972 (Box 1)
    - Resolutions, Statements, and Reactions 1958-1969, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - State Conferences 1968, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Treasurer's Reports 1958-1972 (Box 1)
    - Youth Authority Legislation undated (Box 1)
    - Youth Council 1966-1973 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Concerns
    The Ann Arbor Concerns subseries covers a wide array of topics that directly affected Ann Arbor residents. The growth of the Ann Arbor Community Center, an organization which played an important role in the social life of African-American citizens, is documented in a folder which contains historical information about the role it played from 1938 to 1963. Housing materials range in date from the period before there was a Housing Commission through to the late 1960s. Included are housing ordinance proposals and fair housing case files. Of particular interest is a housing study complied by Jenny Newman in 1962-1963 that illustrated the breakdown of Ann Arbor housing at this time and the Fair Housing Association/CORE folder that includes a "Tour for Better Housing" of some of the worst rental housing existing in Ann Arbor. Examples of some of the advertisements appearing in local newspapers are also included in these folders. Included in the Human Relations Commission files, dating from its inception, are reports, statements, minutes and other supporting material.
    Emma Wheeler's fight for integration and a racially just discipline policy in the public schools are documented in the Schools folders. Among the material in these folders are several reports from the Ann Arbor schools and supporting files used by the NAACP in forming the basis of their decisions. These files follow integration from 1963 to 1969 as well as attempts within the school to combat racism and provide for minority inclusion in the curriculum. Mrs. Wheeler was active in attempts to redefine the school discipline policy from 1968 to 1972.
    - Civic Forum 1950-1951 (Box 1)
    - Community Center 1938-1964 (Box 1)
    - Economic Opportunities Act undated (Box 1)
    - Enablers Anonymous undated (Box 1)
    - Fair Housing Cases 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Fair Housing Association/CORE 1962-1968 (Box 1)
    - Housing Commission 1965-1969 (Box 2)
    - Housing, Miscellaneous 1963-1968 (Box 2)
    - Housing Ordinance 1963-1965 (Box 2)
    - Housing Rule 9 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - Housing Study 1962-1963 (Box 2)
    - Human Relations Commission
      - Cooperative Occupational Training Program 1967 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1954-1969 (Box 2)
      - Housing 1947-1966 (Box 2)
      - Minutes 1957-1963 (Box 2)
      - Reports 1957-1958 (Box 2)
      - Reports undated (Box 2)
      - Statements/Reports 1960-1967 (Box 2)
    - Model Cities 1969-1975, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Model Cities Health Clinic Board 1972 (Box 2)
    - Neighborhood Rehabilitation Improvement Committee 1959-1967 (Box 2)
    - North Central Property Owners Association 1971-1975 (Box 2)
    - Planning Commission 1962-1969 (Box 2)
    - Pre-Housing Commission 1959-1965 (Box 2)
    - Schools
      - Combating Racism 1965-1971 (Box 2)
      - Discipline Policy 1968-1972 (Box 2)
      - Drop Out Study 1970 (Box 2)
      - Graduation Study 1961 (Box 2)
      - Integration 1963-1969 (Box 2)
      - Minority Curriculum Inclusion 1970 (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous Statements, Memos, Correspondence 1966-1971 (Box 2)
      - New Schools Construction 1972 (Box 2)
      - Pioneer/Huron High Student Demands and Statements 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - Transportation System 1973 (Box 2)
    - Urban Renewal
      - Correspondence, Resolutions, Proposals 1956-1959 (Box 2)
      - General Information, Maps 1956-1969 (Box 2)
      - Standards Plan Committee, Minutes 1958 (Box 2)
  - Washtenaw County Concerns
    The Washtenaw County files are primarily materials of the Citizens for Economic Opportunity Commission and include minutes, reports and correspondence, as well as other issues unique to this organization.
    - Committee for Economic Opportunity
      - Correspondence 1964-1968, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Legal Aid 1966-1967 (Box 3)
      - Minutes 1965-1967, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Statements and Reports (Box 3)
    - Prisoner Treatment 1964 (Box 3)
    - Social Welfare 1963 (Box 3)
    - Willow Run Association for Neighborhood Development (WRAND) 1963-1967 (Box 3)
  - Topical Files
    The Topical Files subseries includes Law Enforcement/Courts and Employment Practices folders which document cases of particular interest to the NAACP because of allegations of racial discrimination. The NAACP and the Wheelers were often sought out in such cases. The Community Organizations files reflect attempts by various groups in Ann Arbor to join together on civil rights issues. Included in the Michigan files is the important work done by Dr. Wheeler to assure establishment of the state Civil Rights Commission as well as other statements and proposals from the Constitutional Convention of 1961. Later correspondence from the commission is also included.
    - Law Enforcement and Courts
      - Ann Arbor Police 1964-1970 (Box 3)
      - State and Local Courts 1964-1968 (Box 3)
      - State Police, Sheriff 1964-1968 (Box 3)
    - Employment Practices
      - Ann Arbor 1957-1972 (Box 3)
      - Annapolis Hospital Case 1963-1965 (Box 3)
      - Michigan Fair Employment Practices Commission 1961 (Box 3)
      - Michigan Highway Department 1961 (Box 3)
      - University of Michigan 1964-1972 (Box 3)
    - Child Care
      - Community Coordinated Child Care 1971-1972 (Box 3)
      - Experimental Nursery School undated (Box 3)
      - Wrand Day Care Center 1968-1969 (Box 3)
    - Community Organizations
      - Bethel AME Church 1963-1964 (Box 3)
      - Black/Jewish Celebration 1989 (Box 3)
      - Civil Rights Coordinating Council 1964-1967 (Box 3)
      - Conference on Race and Religion 1956-1964 (Box 3)
      - YMCA undated (Box 3)
    - Michigan
      - Black Urban Affairs Conference undated (Box 3)
      - Civil Rights Commission
        - Correspondence
          - 1961-1963 (Box 3)
          - 1965-1968 (Box 3)
        - Statements, Proposals 1961-1967 (Box 3)
      - Education 1954-1971 (Box 3)
      - Ferris College Incident undated (Box 3)
      - Jobs For Youth 1969 (Box 3)
      - Juvenile Delinquency 1968-1969 (Box 3)
      - Michigan Catholic Conference 1961-1974 (Box 3)
      - Michigan Conference of NAACP Branches 1969 (Box 3)
      - Michigan Welfare League 1966-1968 (Box 3)
      - Statewide Housing Conference 1968 (Box 3)
    - Race Relations Issues 1963-1970 (Box 3)
    - Clippings (Box 3)
  - Presidential Files
    The Presidential Files subseries provides information about the activities of the local Michigan chapters of the NAACP and the state president, Dr. Wheeler. Some of the correspondence is of a somewhat routine nature, yet it serves an important role, in that it documents the Michigan NAACP. The Correspondence folders are arranged alphabetically by corespondent name and the Branches are arranged alphabetically by branch name. Included are various reports, statements and other documents, as well as clippings, which serve as a record of the local branches. Other folders contain reports, statements and correspondence with regard to issues of importance to the NAACP.
    - Correspondence, Alphabetical, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Branches, Alphabetical, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Constitution 1968 (Box 3)
    - Directives to Branches 1966-1968 (Box 3)
    - Education 1966-1969 (Box 3)
    - Employment 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - Freedom Fund Dance 1964 (Box 4)
    - Housing 1966 (Box 4)
    - Police-Community Relations 1968 (Box 4)
    - Police Recruitment Project 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Political Action 1964-1967 (Box 4)
    - Resolutions 1965-1968 (Box 4)
    - State Conference 1960-1968, 2 folders
      - Minutes 1966-1968 (Box 4)
    - Treasurer's Reports 1966-1967 (Box 4)
    - Youth Councils 1966-1967 (Box 4)
- Mayoral Files 1975-1978
  The Mayoral Files series (1975-1978; 1.75 linear feet) includes those items unique to Albert Wheeler's tenure as mayor of Ann Arbor. Materials of a routine nature, such as committee reports, minutes, and memoranda have generally not been retained in this collection, as these items would be maintained by the city of Ann Arbor. The mayoral elections in which Albert Wheeler ran in 1975 and 1977, both of which were decided in a manner out of the ordinary, and not without controversy, are documented through court documents, reports and correspondence. Proclamations, resolutions, press releases and vetoes of Mayor Wheeler are included, as are a folder of speeches and remarks made in his capacity as mayor.
  The Correspondence files contain a large amount of correspondence received by Mayor Wheeler, reflecting citizen concerns and those issues that tended to provoke citizens to write to the mayor. Federal funding in the Community Development Revenue Sharing (CDRS) program brought about large numbers of organizations seeking mayoral approval for their programs. The complaints received by Mayor Wheeler range anywhere from parking, to senior citizen housing, to the dog leash law. By far the greater bulk of correspondence of this nature was received in 1975 after Wheeler took office. The complaints tend not to be aimed directly at Wheeler, but rather at city policies and ordinances.
  Citizen correspondence is also included in Congratulatory, Thank You, and General files. The involvement of the Wheeler administration in both the Community Development Block Grant (CDBG) and Comprehensive Employment Training Act (CETA) resulted in correspondence from both Presidents Ford and Carter. This correspondence is in the White House folder.
  The Topical Files include various commissions, departments, ordinances, and issues. Of particular interest are the Fair Rental Practices Commission and the Human Services Department. Both of these were established by Wheeler in 1975 in keeping with his campaign promises. Charges of conflict of interest are documented in the Model Cities folder, which raises concerns that Mrs. Wheeler's unpaid appointment as chair of the Model Cities Health Center was in direct conflict with Wheeler's role as mayor.